Hi!
It's been a while since my previous
ElectroBOOM 101 video,
...which was about
...resistors. Right.
But there's no point to go any further
without knowing what a circuit is.
What is a circuit?
Well, you always need a power supply
(like the AC source)
...and a load.
Let me...
...make some room.
I just need to...
...clean in front of the camera.
Like a microwave oven, for example.
I can put in the
...plastic fan, I guess.
It's not gonna heat up because it is plastic.
Now if I turn it on,
...it draws power from the supply
...to heat up the-
How does it work!?
If there is metal in something,
...don't put it in the microwave.
Just burned my No.1 fan.
And don't just throw fire on your pile of junk.
H H H ∀ ∀ ∀ ∀ ∀
We can use a lamp for example,
...as the lo-
You know, a lot of smart people do a very decent job of
...teaching their knowledge and skills at
...the sponsor of this video!
The online learning community.
Thousands of classes!
And none of them is likely to set your home on fire.
You can surely find what you like or need to learn
...from the list of many categories
...for free!
For the first two months, that is,
...IF you use my link to sign up,
...after which the annual subscription
is less than $10 a month,
...which is nothing compared to the value of knowledge.
Let's continue on the whiteboard.
Simply put, every circuit is made of two parts:
A power supply which pukes out power,
...and a load that eats up power.
The power supply generates electric current
...by placing voltage across the load.
Of course, energy can escape the system
...in form of light, heat, radiation and such,
...but the electric charges, like electrons,
...MUST return to the source,
...and thats why all active circuits are always closed.
ALWAYS!
It is like the flow of water
...turning a generator.
As we rely on the water cycle to return
the water back into the hose,
...the electric charges must
also return back to the source.
Otherwise, we'll run out of charges to push out
...and the current stops.
So, if I supposedly open the circuit,
...but the light continues glowing a bit,
...it's because the circuit never really opened.
If the circuit seems open
...but your load is still powered,
...then you must be missing a component in your circuit,
...which in this case
...is a stray capacitor made through
the excess length of the wire,
...which blocks DC, but passes AC through.
So you must be careful about why
you're drawing a schematic.
There are two main types of schematic.
One is simply to show the components
you have in your design
...and how to connect them.
This is typically for manufacturing
or troubleshooting purposes,
Pretty straightforward.
You just draw it to be most readable,
...and these lines show how your components
connect by conductors like wire.
But, another type of schematic
...is what you draw to analyze a circuit.
In such a schematic,
...the results are as accurate as the models
you pick for your circuits and components.
So, there might be a capacitor
...parallel to your switch.
Your supply would have an output impedance.
Your wires would have
...series resistive and inductive components.
Your load
...might have an antenna component
radiating electromagnetic waves.
But don't let this intimidate you.
As a designer, you need to know that these exist
...and you will learn when to ignore them,
...unlike the designers of these LED light bulbs,
...who decided to ignore the line
capacitance and let the lamp glow.
So, in every schematic there are
components and their connections.
Components connect together
...through these connecting lines by their terminals.
Components can have one terminal, like an antenna.
Two terminals is the most common one
...like resistors, capacitors, inductors,
supply, diodes and such.
Three terminals is like transistors,
Four terminals and above are like ICs,
...like amplifiers, processors and such.
The connecting line's properties
depend on the type of schematic.
Again, if you are using this for
manufacturing or troubleshooting,
...then these lines only show how
the components are connected,
...ignoring the wire resistance or
other straight components.
But for analyzing a circuit, which is our focus here,
...these are not regular wires.
Nothing about them is regular.
They are magic wires!
Even superconductors don't come
close to what these wires are!
These are ideal connections
connecting point A to point B,
...with absolutely 0 ohm between them.
It doesn't matter how long the wire is,
...or how many locations it connects to.
The line itself does not affect your circuit.
These ideal connections have no stray inductance
...no matter how long the wires are,
...and there's no stray capacitance between the lines,
...no matter how close you draw them on paper.
These are SUPER WIRES!
Nobody calls them that though.
It is important to know that these are ideal connections.
And you must realise that in real life
...you will use actual wires that will have
stray components like I mentioned
...that will affect the behaviour of the circuit.
But don't worry.
The engineering design involves a whole bunch
of approximations and assumptions.
So for most purposes,
...such a connection is a pretty
good approximation of a wire.
But if the straight component of
a wire becomes too significant,
...you can show it in your schematic model
...to make the behavior better to understand
...and your calculations more accurate.
For example, in one of my videos,
...I made the
...resistor
...using this very thick, low-resistance wire.
Although for most purposes
this thick-a** wire is a 0-ohm,
...for my purpose, I used it as a shunt resistor,
...and so must show it as a resistor.
Now, when a line connects to another line,
...it creates a node.
A node is a location where
...two or more branches connect to each other.
And like those magical connections,
...the nodes have no affect on your circuit
...beside connecting the branches.
So if you connect components like this,
...all these connections are no
different than a single node.
Because since these are connected with magic lines,
...the line length and the number of nodes don't matter.
So you're free to draw your
schematic to make it look pretty.
Okay, I hope I'm not going too fast.
Let's do some intermission.
Enough intermission.
Okay, let's repeat.
In a circuit,
...there are components
...that their terminals connect to each other
...using magic wires.
Two or more connections from different branches
...can join in a node.
Now let's talk about series and parallel.
These two are the simplest connections in a circuit
...that can help simplify our calculations.
Let's assume you have a component
...like a resistor or a capacitor
...or a complex circuit like a computer that you
can contain all of the circuit in a black box
...with only two terminals going in and out of it.
If you have two of such components
...connected together by one terminal each,
...then these two are in series.
If both their terminals are connected like this,
...then they are in parallel.
If there are only two components in a circuit like this,
...then they are both in series and parallel,
...like a supply and a lamp.
Let's do some examples.
These four components are in series.
If I connect another component
between these two nodes,
...then
...these two (C1-2)
...and these two (C3-4)
...are not series anymore.
But these two (C2-3) are still in series,
...and this (C5) is in parallel with this branch (C2-3)
And these three (C1, C5 & 2-3, C4) are still in series.
Or here,
...these two components (C1-2) are in series
...and those two components (C3-4) are in series
...and this whole branch (C1-2) is in
parallel with the other branch (C3-4).
But if I add a component between these two nodes,
...then nothing here is either in series or parallel.
But the whole thing is still in parallel
with the rest of the circuit.
Now, there are important properties
to series and parallel connections
...that you must never forget.
NEVER!
Are you ready?
When components are in SERIES,
...the electric CURRENT through
all of them is exactly the same,
...because electric charges are not leaking anywhere.
So if the current enters the branch,
...it must go through it, unchanged.
You know what this means?
We can switch the location of the
components in a series branch,
...and it doesn't affect the circuit,
...because the current through all of them is equal.
In PARALLEL circuits,
...the VOLTAGE across all components
are exactly the same,
...because otherwise,
...there would be a voltage difference
across a 0-ohm magic wire,
...which would result in infinite current,
...which is impossible.
And you know what that means?
In parallel circuits, you can switch
the location of the components,
...and it doesn't make any difference
...because the voltage across them remains the same.
Like at home,
...if you switch the location of your TV and your lamp,
...it doesn't make any difference.
This reminds me of the disagreement I had
with Professor Lewin in my other video,
...where he was claiming that
...the voltages across two parallel
components can be different
...in the presence of changing magnetic fields.
The summary was that our definitions were different,
...and my definition was better, of course.
In any case,
...the properties of series and
parallel circuits never break.
If you measure two DIFFERENT CURRENTS
between SERIES components,
...it must mean that the current is leaking out of
the branch through some hidden component,
...and these two are not actually in series.
Or if you measure two DIFFERENT VOLTAGES
across PARALLEL components,
...it means that they are not in parallel
...and there must be a hidden component
between them you didn't account for.
These should be enough for one video.
If you like this type of video where
someone like me shares their skills,
Then you'll love
Two months of free premium subscription, mate!
Just use my link in the description and sign up.
And there you'll find a vast community of people
...teaching what they know professionally,
...like, uh...
...lessons on Arduino is still going through,
...or from other categories like animation or film,
...that can help my work.
I still need to learn some Adobe Premiere film editing.
LEARNING FOR FREE HASN'T KILLED ANYBODY!
So sign up for free for the two-month
free trial and get the unlimited access,
...and I'm sure you'll be hooked.
Oh
Have fun.
Subtitles/captions by Jonathan Lee (Pentameron)
youtube.com/c/PentameronSV